<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="/static/oohdir/xsl/pretty-feed-v3a.xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>ooh.directory blog</title><link>https://ooh.directory/blog/</link><description>Changes and events at ooh.directory</description><atom:link href="https://ooh.directory/blog/feeds/posts.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2023 15:45:40 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://ooh.directory/static/oohdir/img/site_icon.png</url><title>ooh.directory blog</title><link>https://ooh.directory/blog/</link></image><item><title>What does recently updated mean?</title><link>https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/recently-fetched-published/</link><description>You might be familiar with the Recently updated blogs page, which shows a list of blogs ordered by those that posted most recently. It can be a nice way to see what people are blogging about right now. In fact, in a recent blog post, Warren Ellis said:


the&amp;amp;nbsp;ooh.directory recently updated blogs list&amp;amp;nbsp;is what I have instead of social media if I’m in the mood to “waste” time on my phone


Which sounds like a great idea. However, a while back I realised a small problem with the page.&amp;amp;nbsp;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Phil Gyford</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2023 14:10:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/recently-fetched-published/</guid><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You might be familiar with the <a href="https://ooh.directory/updated/">Recently updated blogs page</a>, which shows a list of blogs ordered by those that posted most recently. It can be a nice way to see what people are blogging about right now. In fact, in <a href="https://warrenellis.ltd/jot/random-notes-10jul23/">a recent blog post</a>, Warren Ellis said:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>the&nbsp;<a href="https://ooh.directory/updated/">ooh.directory recently updated blogs list&nbsp;</a>is what I have instead of social media if I’m in the mood to “waste” time on my phone</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Which sounds like a great idea. However, a while back I realised a small problem with the page.&nbsp;</p>
<p><em>(If this is too much to read, jump down to the <strong>bold paragraph</strong> below for what's actually changed.)</em></p>

<p>The blogs were ordered by when their most recent post was published. Which makes sense. Except there's a delay between when a post is published and when ooh.directory next looks at that blog's feed and notices the new post.</p>

<p>The frequency with which we check blogs' feeds varies. A blog that posts often will be checked more frequently. But each time we check a feed and find there's no new post, we increase the time between checks. There's no point checking a blog every hour if it only posts once a year.</p>

<p>The biggest gap we leave between checking a blog's feed is currently 24 hours. Which can mean that if a rarely-updated blog publishes a new post at noon on a Friday, it might only appear on ooh.directory as late as noon on Saturday (although on average it'll be sooner).</p>

<p>So, imagine ooh.directory only picks up that post at noon on Saturday. And you visit the Recently updated blogs page at 12.01pm that day. That post – only just fetched – was <em>published</em> a whole day ago. Between then and now, many other blogs will have published new posts, so that blog would appear quite a way down the list, probably a few pages away.</p>

<p>Given that blogs that update rarely&nbsp;<em>can</em>&nbsp;be among the most interesting, this seemed a shame.</p>

<p><strong>To stop rarely-updated blogs from getting lost in this list, the page is now ordered by when each blog's latest post was <em>found</em> by ooh.directory, instead of when it was&nbsp;<em>published</em>.</strong></p>

<p>This does mean that a post appearing on the first page, marked "4 minutes ago" might actually have been published hours ago, or even the previous day. But it only arrived on the site four minutes ago. This feels fairer and more transparent. It's everything coming in to ooh.directory, as it arrives.</p>

<p>Over time, with more resources (and confidence in the server and code) we might increase the frequency with which we fetch feeds for all blogs, which would reduce the potential gap between a post being published, and a post arriving on the site. But for now we'll see how this change goes – hopefully it means rarely-updated blogs will be more visible in the stream when you're "wasting" time on your phone.</p>

<p>If you visit the Recently updated blogs page frequently, and have any thoughts on this change, or how else to improve the page, then do get in touch&nbsp;via&nbsp;<a href="https://mastodon.social/@oohdirectory">Mastodon</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://twitter.com/oohdirectory">Twitter</a>&nbsp;or&nbsp;<a href="mailto:phil@gyford.com?subject=Recently%20updated%20blogs%20page">email</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Awards, noisy blogs, images, and revived blogs</title><link>https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/awards-noisy-images-revived/</link><description>Four things are gathered in this one post…

First, I&amp;#x27;m pleased to announce that ooh.directory is a nominee for the Tiny Awards, alongside 15 other little websites. If you&amp;#x27;d like to vote for this site (listed as &amp;quot;Ooh! directory&amp;quot;) or any of the others, you can do so on the voting page&amp;amp;nbsp;before 20th July.
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Phil Gyford</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 17:30:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/awards-noisy-images-revived/</guid><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Four things are gathered in this one post…</p>

<p>First, I'm pleased to announce that <strong>ooh.directory is a nominee for the <a href="https://tinyawards.net">Tiny Awards</a></strong>, alongside 15 other little websites. If you'd like to vote for this site (listed as "Ooh! directory") or any of the others, you can do so <a href="https://tally.so/r/3yNAMd">on the voting page</a>&nbsp;before 20th July.</p>
<hr />
<p>Second, there were some helpful responses following <a href="https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/noisiest-blogs/">the previous post</a> about blogs that post many, many times per day (thanks all!). Following that <strong>we've removed a dozen of the busiest blogs</strong> from the directory and we'll see how that feels. Hopefully this makes the <a href="https://ooh.directory/updated/">Recently updated blogs page</a>&nbsp;more interesting and varied, and tilts the site slightly more towards "small interesting blogs" and away from "large 'news' websites".</p>

<hr />
<p>Third, <strong>every category page now has its own emoji-based images</strong> to use for prettier previews on the rare occasion that its URL is shared on Twitter, Facebook, etc.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/opml-rss-categories/">Each category's RSS feed</a>&nbsp;also uses those images</strong>, which means that some feed readers will show that next to the feed's title. In my limited testing this is true for <a href="https://feedbin.com">Feedbin</a> but not <a href="https://netnewswire.com">NetNewsWire</a> or <a href="https://feedly.com">Feedly</a>&nbsp;which both continue to use the site's Favicon.</p>

<hr />
<p>Fourth, and finally, as well as the home page highlighting blogs <a href="https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/blog-birthdays/">celebrating a significant birthday</a> today, <strong>if a blog publishes its first post in a long time</strong>, that will be celebrated on the home page too. (What "a long time" is may change, depending on how this goes.)</p>

<p><img alt="A screenshot of part of the home page with the headline &quot;First post in almost a year!&quot; The blog is &quot;The lost output&quot; and the post shown is titled &quot;Running a 3D print catalogue with Van Dam&quot; by Andy Piper." src="/media/uploads/2023/07/05/revived_post.png" style="height:706px; width:1240px" /></p>

<p>It's great if you have something to blog about regularly but it's also fine if you rarely post on your blog. There are no blogging rules! In the latter case it seemed worth a tiny "ooh, look, nice!" when a blog wakes up again.</p>

<hr />
<p>That's all for now. As ever, feedback via&nbsp;<a href="https://mastodon.social/@oohdirectory">Mastodon</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/oohdirectory">Twitter</a> or <a href="mailto:phil@gyford.com">email</a>&nbsp;is always appreciated.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The noisiest blogs</title><link>https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/noisiest-blogs/</link><description>A while back we added a way to filter the Recently updated blogs page to hide blogs that post frequently. This is useful to hide the noisiest sites and make updates from the quieter ones more noticeable. But are the very busiest blogs too noisy to even feature in the directory? Are they even blogs?
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Phil Gyford</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 15:00:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/noisiest-blogs/</guid><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A while back we <a href="https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/posting-frequencies/">added a way to filter</a> the <a href="https://ooh.directory/updated/">Recently updated blogs page</a> to hide blogs that post frequently. This is useful to hide the noisiest sites and make updates from the quieter ones more noticeable. But are the very busiest blogs too noisy to even feature in the directory? Are they even blogs?</p>
<p>First let's look at the stats. Here are the blogs that post most frequently, ordered by the average number of posts they publish per day:</p>

<table class="table">
	<thead>
		<tr>
			<th>Position</th>
			<th>Blog</th>
			<th>Average posts per day</th>
		</tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">1</td>
			<td><a href="https://medicalxpress.com/">Medical Xpress</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">61</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">2</td>
			<td><a href="https://lifeboat.com/blog/">Lifeboat Foundation News Blog</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">45</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">3</td>
			<td><a href="https://phys.org/biology-news/">Biology News</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">23</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">4=</td>
			<td><a href="https://techxplore.com/">Tech Xplore</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">19</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">4=</td>
			<td><a href="https://www.stereogum.com/">Stereogum</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">19</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">6</td>
			<td><a href="https://www.archdaily.com/">ArchDaily</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">17</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">7</td>
			<td><a href="https://phys.org/earth-news/">Earth News</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">13</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">8</td>
			<td><a href="https://thepointsguy.com/">The Points Guy</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">12</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">9</td>
			<td><a href="https://www.dezeen.com/">Dezeen</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">11</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">10=</td>
			<td><a href="https://westseattleblog.com">West Seattle Blog</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">10</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">10=</td>
			<td><a href="https://3quarksdaily.com/">3 Quarks Daily</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">10</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">10=</td>
			<td><a href="https://www.lawyersgunsmoneyblog.com/">Lawyers, Guns &amp; Money</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">10</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">10=</td>
			<td><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/">MacRumors</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">10</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">10=</td>
			<td><a href="https://hackaday.com/">Hackaday</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">10</td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>

<p>An average of 61 posts per day (427 per week)&nbsp;is, shall we say, rather chatty! Especially considering that's the average – some days will be even busier.</p>

<p>As a comparison, here are some well-known blogs selected from a little further down the list:</p>

<table class="table">
	<thead>
		<tr>
			<th>Position</th>
			<th>Blog</th>
			<th>Average posts per day</th>
		</tr>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">15=</td>
			<td><a href="https://www.atlasobscura.com/">Atlas Obscura</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">9</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">22=</td>
			<td><a href="https://conservativehome.com/">Conservative Home</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">7</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">28=</td>
			<td><a href="http://scripting.com/">Scripting News</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">6</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">47=</td>
			<td><a href="https://www.ianvisits.co.uk/articles/">ianVisits</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">3</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">47=</td>
			<td><a href="https://www.askamanager.org/">Ask a Manager</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">3</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">47=</td>
			<td><a href="https://daringfireball.net/">Daring Fireball</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">3</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">71=</td>
			<td><a href="https://kottke.org/">kottke.org</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">2</td>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<td class="text-align-right">71=</td>
			<td><a href="https://waxy.org/">Waxy.org</a></td>
			<td class="text-align-right">2</td>
		</tr>
	</tbody>
</table>

<p>As a further comparison, the median number of posts per day is about 0.07. That's around two posts per <em>month</em>. Which is fine – there are no rules about how often you should blog! But it illustrates the wide range of posting frequencies: from two posts per month up to around 1,800 per month.</p>

<p>How does this affect ooh.directory? It feels like the most frequently-posting blogs are extreme, and taking up far more attention and resources than the majority. But it's unclear if this is a problem and, if so, what to do about it.</p>

<p>We could decide that the noisiest blogs are "news sites" instead of blogs and disqualify them. But there are going to be grey areas when deciding this and adjudicating what is or isn't a blog seems tedious. <a href="https://medicalxpress.com">Medical Xpress</a>, the noisiest, <em>looks</em> like a blog and has an RSS feed, so surely it's a blog?</p>

<p>We could decide that professional blogs aren't allowed here, but that's another set of difficult decisions. Anyone making a living from their blog is "professional" but it would be silly to disqualify <a href="https://kottke.org">kottke.org</a>, for example, on that basis.</p>

<p>We could decide a cut-off point of post-frequency, above which blogs aren't included. "Anything posting 10 or more times a day is a 'news site', and that's not what this directory is for". If so, what should that number be?</p>

<p>If you've read this far, what do you think? I'm keen to hear thoughts from other people before making any decision. Let me know on <a href="https://mastodon.social/@oohdirectory">Mastodon</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/oohdirectory">Twitter</a> or <a href="mailto:phil@gyford.com?subject=The%20noisiest%20blogs">by email</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Blog birthdays</title><link>https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/blog-birthdays/</link><description>We&amp;#x27;re keen to have the site&amp;#x27;s front page display interesting things even if we haven&amp;#x27;t been able to add new blogs to the site for a few days.

So we recently started highlighting any blogs that have notable birthdays today. Any blog that&amp;#x27;s having its 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 5th, 10th, or 20th birthday, and that published a post within the past couple of months or so, will be highlighted on the front page.
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Phil Gyford</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 16:59:52 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/blog-birthdays/</guid><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We're keen to have the site's front page display interesting things even if we haven't been able to add new blogs to the site for a few days.</p>

<p>So we recently started highlighting any blogs that have notable birthdays today. Any blog that's having its 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 5th, 10th, or 20th birthday, and that published a post within the past couple of months or so, will be highlighted on the front page.</p>
<p><img alt="A screenshot showing listings for two blogs: &quot;Lat x Long&quot; celebrating its first birthday today, and &quot;Ben Werdmuller&quot; celebrating 10 years" src="/media/uploads/2023/05/31/blog_birthdays.png" style="height:834px; width:1270px" /></p>

<p>It's a nice way to celebrate blogs that have stuck around, and to unearth blogs from the depths of the directory that you might not have come across before. Over time, we might tweak which birthdays we celebrate: the current birthday choice often means there are days with nothing to celebrate.</p>

<hr />
<p>Of course, to know if it's a blog's birthday, we need to know the date of its first post. Whenever we add a new blog to the directory we look for its first post and save the date. This is easy to do if:</p>

<ul>
	<li>There's a dated list of posts in the sidebar (hello, Blogspot blogs!)</li>
	<li>Or there's a dropdown that links to monthly archive pages (hello, some WordPress templates!)</li>
	<li>Or there's a link to an archive page listing all&nbsp;posts in date order</li>
	<li>Or the bottom of the front page links to previous pages of posts and it's easy to jump directly to the oldest page</li>
</ul>

<p>It's possible, but more time consuming, if:</p>

<ul>
	<li>The bottom of the front page links to previous pages of posts but there's no way to know how many pages there are. In this case, if the URLs are sensible, like <strong>/page/2/</strong>,&nbsp;we use trial and error,&nbsp;changing the URL several times until we find the oldest page</li>
</ul>

<p>Unfortunately some sites make it too time-consuming, or even impossible, to find their first post. This could be because:</p>

<ul>
	<li>Their previous pages' URLs use dates instead of page numbers, so there's no easy way to find the first one</li>
	<li>Or, instead of separate pages, their front page has an infinte scroll of freshly-loading older posts, but the URL never changes. We're not going to keep scrolling until we get to the first post! (hello, some Medium blogs!)</li>
	<li>Or, there's no pagination, no easy way to find dated archives, no chronological lists of posts. It's hardly even a blog at this point.</li>
</ul>

<p>All of which is to say: why make it hard to find your first post, or even the posts from a certain time period? If we can easily find when your blog was born then we can all celebrate its birthday!</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Category RSS feeds now notify you of new sub-categories</title><link>https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/category-feeds-sub-categories/</link><description>A while back&amp;amp;nbsp;we added an RSS feed for every category. These will now notify you about new sub-categories, as well as new blogs, within the category.
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Phil Gyford</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 15:09:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/category-feeds-sub-categories/</guid><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A while back&nbsp;<a href="https://ooh.directory/blog/2023/opml-rss-categories/">we added an RSS feed for every category</a>. These will now notify you about new sub-categories, as well as new blogs, within the category.</p>
<p>An example…</p>

<p>Let's imagine you follow the RSS feed for <a href="https://ooh.directory/blogs/recreation/food-and-drink/drink/">the Drink category</a>. The feed updates whenever a new blog is added to Drink, but not when a blog is added to any sub-categories, which currently are only&nbsp;<a href="https://ooh.directory/blogs/recreation/food-and-drink/drink/beer/">Beer</a> and <a href="https://ooh.directory/blogs/recreation/food-and-drink/drink/coffee/">Coffee</a>.</p>

<p>This is fine: you love wine so you're mainly following the Drink category for any new wine blogs.</p>

<p>But if we added a new Wine sub-category within Drink, and started adding wine blogs to it, you would never know.</p>

<p>But now, you'll get an item in your Drink category feed that reads:</p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>🎉 New sub-category: Wine</strong></p>

<p>This sub-category was added within Drink.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So you can follow the link to view the Wine sub-category and, if you want, subscribe to its own RSS feed.</p>

<p>Only immediate sub-categories are included. If we added Lager and Ale sub-categories within Beer then you, as a follower of Drink, wouldn't be notified. Only followers of the Beer feed would.</p>

<p>Hopefully that makes sense and will help keep you up-to-date with the latest in your favourite blogging topics.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>